Theatre Collection MS091
Tufts Archival Research Center
Theatre Collection
1867 -- 1981
Tufts Archival Research Center
Digital Collections and Archives
MS091
4.85 Linear Feet 7 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Playbills, souvenir programs and periodicals; Images.
Custodial History
Around 2003, several artificial collections were created from material found in Henry Y. Porter, Max Tennis and the Frank E. Fowle papers. One of these was the MS091 collection. The MS091 collection largely consists of items that have either been found with other collections but cannot be identified with a specific collection, or are donated materials prior to the establishment of the DCA and no collection documentation exists to indicate where it came from.
Scope and Contents
This is an artificial collection consisting of material related to theater productions including playbills, souvenir programs, periodicals, and images. Most of the collection relates to late nineteenth and early twentieth century plays in New York as well as the greater Boston area.
Biographical / Historical
Tufts Archival Research Center is the Tufts University steward for all archival records and materials of significant and historical relevance to the college.
The collection began as the University Archives, which were incorporated in 1965 by the Tufts University Board of Trustees (Annual Reports 1965-1988). Previously, the position of archivist was loosely created in 1959 as a means of processing and acquiring important university and student records for preservation. This role was filled by Tufts history professor and historian Russell L. Miller, who also wrote the Tufts University history "Light on the Hill." The archives were considered a department of the University Library (known as Eaton and then Wessell at that time), overseen by the College of Arts, Sciences and Engineering.
The university's archives were first kept in Eaton Library, but moved to the Wessell Library building in 1965. Originals of some records were sent to vaults in Ballou Hall for storage. In 1991, due to budget issues, the university archivist was laid off. When the office was reopened in 1997, it was as the University Archives and Special Collections, also located as a department within the Tisch Library.
In July 2001, Digital Collections and Archives (DCA) was created when the University Archives was tasked with developing a Tufts Digital Library. The department moved from the College of Arts, Science and Engineering to the Central Administration, directed by the University Provost. The Special Collections department remained under Tisch Library.
In January 2023, DCA was renamed Tufts Archival Research Center (TARC) to better reflect the mission and services offered by the department.
TARC is currently physically housed in the Tisch Library building.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Theater; Greater Boston arts
- Playbills, souvenir progams and periodicals, 1867 -- 1981; 1894 -- 1915; MS091.001; 2.7 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series of playbills includes examples from late nineteenth and early twentieth century productions of plays mostly produced in the Northeast. One select part of the collection includes a card cataloged inventory by title of play and name of actor (found in Boxes 1 and 2). There are also some souvenir programs from films and a year's worth of the periodical, a Gallery of Players.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged as found.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Playbills, American theatres, 1899 -- 1938; MS091.001.001
    Located in Baltimore, MD; Boston, MA; Springfield, MA.
    - Broadway Theatre Magazine, Springfield, MA, 1913; MS091.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    - Poli's Theatre, Springfield, MA, 1911 -- 1914; MS091.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    - Wilbur Theatre, Boston, MA, 1914 -- 1933; MS091.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
    - Globe Theatre, Boston, MA, 1903 -- 1904; MS091.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    - St. James Theatre, Boston, MA, 1925 -- 1927; MS091.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    - Colonial Theatre, Boston, MA, 1902 -- 1925; MS091.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
    - Colonial Theatre, Boston, MA, 1927 -- 1938; MS091.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
    - Plymouth Theatre, Boston, MA, 1913 -- 1934; MS091.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    - Tremont Theatre, Boston, MA, 1901 -- 1933; MS091.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
    - Court Square Theatre, Springfield, MA, 1910 -- 1914; MS091.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
    - B.F. Keith, Boston, MA, 1924 -- 1927; MS091.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
    - University Theatre, Cambridge, MA, 1926; MS091.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
    - Selwyn's Theatre, Boston, MA, 1924; MS091.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
    - Grand Opera House, Boston, MA, 1902 -- 1904; MS091.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
    - Boston Museum, 1902 -- 1903; MS091.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
    - Various Theatres Outside of Boston, 1904 -- 1929; MS091.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
    - Boston Theatres, 1911 -- 1930; MS091.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
    - Chase's Theatre, Baltimore, MD, 1901 -- 1902; MS091.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
    - Academy of Music, Baltimore, MD, 1899 -- 1908; MS091.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
    - Ford's Theatre, Baltimore, MD, 1899 -- 1900; MS091.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
    - Ford's Theatre, Baltimore, MD, 1900 -- 1902; MS091.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
    - Card catalogue of playbills by title and name of actor, 1899 -- 1938; MS091.001.002.001 (Box 2)
      Relates to box 1 in this collection.
  - Periodicals and souvenir booklets, 1894 -- 1939; MS091.001.002
    - Gone with the Wind souvenir booklet, 1939; MS091.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
      Facts and information regarding the film, edited by Howard Dietz.
    - The Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse souvenir booklet, 1921; MS091.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
      Starring Rudolf Valentino.
    - The Movie Builder, March, May, 1931; MS091.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
      A magazine devoted to education for the screen.
    - Andrew Jergen Co., souvenir booklet, read the answers of the stars, MS091.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
    - Scenes from the Latest Plays, December, 1908; MS091.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
      Photos of contemporary productions.
    - Gallery of Players, from the illustrated American, no. 1-6, 1894 -- 1895; MS091.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
      Donated by Elsie Paine in July 1950.
      Paine, Elsie
    - Gallery of Players, from the illustrated American, no. 7-11, 1895 -- 1897; MS091.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
    - Century Theatre souvenir program, 1916; MS091.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
      Charles Dillingham and Florenz Ziegfield, Jr., managers.
  - Medford Shakespeare Club, 1896 -- 1969; MS091.001.003
    Items donated to Tufts from the Medford Shakespeare Club by Mrs. Paul I. Wren in 1975.
    - Weston and Cambridge Shakespeare club rosters, 1955 -- 1967; MS091.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
    - Shakespeare Studies, 1896; MS091.001.004.00002; Richardson, Locke (Box 4)
      "A New interpretation of Falstaff's Dying Words." Belonged to Emily Hallowell.
    - Edwin Booth program from recording of Othello's speech to the Venetian Senate, 1939; MS091.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
      No accompanying album.
    - Christmas card from Shakespeare Center, Stratford-upon-Avon, 1969; MS091.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
      Addressed to Mrs. H.G. Marvel, The Medford Shakespeare Club of Massachusetts.
    - Cabinet cards and postcards of Shakespeare-related people and places, 1900; MS091.001.004.00005 (Box 4)
      Includes images of Folger Library; Shakespeae's gloves; former Palace of King Richard III; Princes in the Tower (Richard III); Shakespeare; Stratford-upon-Avon; Ann Hathaway's Cottage.
    - Letter from Professor G.L. Kittredge to P.H. Savage and reply, 1898; MS091.001.004.00006 (Box 4)
    - Edwin Booth signature card, 1900; MS091.001.004.00007 (Box 4)
      Belonged to Emily Hallowell.
    - Medford Shakespeare Club memorabilia inventory, MS091.001.004.00008 (Box 4)
    - Clippings, 1909 -- 1922; MS091.001.004.00009 (Box 4)
    - Annual report and statement of accounts for the Trustees and Guardians of Shakespeare's Birthplace, 1966 -- 1969; MS091.001.004.00010 (Box 4)
    - Le Bel Amour, 1925; MS091.001.005.00001; See, Edmond (Box 5)
      Playscript published in La Petite Illustration (in french).
  - Playbills, playscripts and periodicals, 1867 -- 1981; MS091.001.004
    - Met in Boston programs, 1980; MS091.001.005.00002 (Box 5)
      Gift of Dr. Tennis (son of Max Tennis?).
    - Boston theatre programs, 1978 -- 1981; MS091.001.005.00003 (Box 5)
      Woman of the Year; On Golden Pond; Wally's Cafe; Sugar Babies; The Mikado and HMS Pinafore; Betrayal; BSO 99th season. Donated by Dr. Tennis (son of Max Tennis?).
    - Cabinet cards (4), 1900; MS091.001.005.00004 (Box 5)
      Edwin Booth; Charles Banon; Annie Clark; and Anna Florence Smith and Peg Sliderskew from Nickolas Nickleby (signed).
    - Unidentified 8x10 group photo with Fred Stone and David Montgomery, MS091.001.005.00005 (Box 5)
      Stone and Montgomery teamed up as a musical comedy duo in early 20th century.
    - Clippings, 'Actors Your Father's Knew', MS091.001.005.00006 (Box 5)
    - The Ray, Musical and Dramatic Times, Boston, Tues., 1801 -- 1880; MS091.001.005.00007 (Box 5)
    - The Women's Street Theatre...This is a Cranky, 1971; MS091.001.005.00008 (Box 5)
      How to publication to make a cranky.
    - Where Thieves break Through Steal, typed playscript, 1912; MS091.001.005.00009; Robinson, Raymond M. (Box 5)
      Original?
    - Belmot Dramatic Club playbills, 1910; MS091.001.005.00010 (Box 5)
    - No Thoroughfare, Christmas, 1867; MS091.001.005.00011; Dickens, Charles; Collins, Wilkie (Box 5)
      2 copies, one a gift of E. Charles Francis, December 1879.
  - Programs, 1916 -- 1963; MS091.001.005
    - Souvenir Program - Jose Greco, MS091.001.006.00001 (Box 6)
    - Information Booklet - The Debuty, 1963; MS091.001.006.00002 (Box 6)
    - Playbill - Amphitryon 38, 1937; MS091.001.006.00003 (Box 6)
    - Souvenir Program - Ballet Russe, 1916; MS091.001.006.00004 (Box 6)
    - Souvenir Book - Fantasia, 1940; MS091.001.006.00005 (Box 6)
      Donated by Marston Balch to Tufts University Library's Theater Collection, 1971-05-21.
    - Souvenir Program - Katharine Cornell stage portraits, MS091.001.006.00006 (Box 6)
    - Souvenir Program - Paul Robeson as Othello, MS091.001.006.00007 (Box 6)
    - Souvenir Program - Richard II with Maurice Evans, MS091.001.006.00008 (Box 6)
    - Souvenir Program - Annie Get Your Gun, MS091.001.006.00009 (Box 6)
- Images, 1890; MS091.002; 1.2 Linear Feet
  This series contains one portrait of Edwin Booth.
  This series contains one image.
  - Portrait of Edwin Booth, 1890; MS091.002.007.00001 (Box Shared 36)
    This image was found uncataloged and wrapped in paper on top of the Special Collections section in the stacks. It has been taken out of its frame for storage purposes. The photograph has the insignia from the well known Frederick F. Gutekunst photography studio in Philadelphia. The portrait is hand-signed however no connection to Tufts has been discovered. Edwin Booth, brother to the infamous John Wilkes Booth, is however buried in Mount Auburn Cemetary in Cambridge. It has been speculated that perhaps he had a connection with a literature professor at Tufts and that is why the image has been found in the Tufts holdings. The art gallery has determined that it is not part of their holdings. Note the location of the material; it is in a box with similarly sized items.